Guide to the Robert Edmond Jones Papers, 1916-1963
Robert Edmond Jones Papers1916 - 1963
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Jones, Robert Edmond, 1887-1954.
1000-165
7.5
8, 1 oversize drawer
Robert Edmond Jones was born in 1887, and spent his career as a theater set designer. He also worked on the production of early Technicolor films as a color consultant. As a stage designer, Jones is best known for his simplified sets that complemented the action of a production and his dramatic use of color in costuming and lighting.
Contains correspondence, manuscript writings, drawings and design materials, photographs, and printed materials. The papers document Jones's work in theater as a set designer in the United States during the early twentieth century and his involvement in motion picture-making during the 1930s.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Given by Ralph G. Pendleton to the Wesleyan Theatre Department in the 1970s. Transferred to Special Collections & Archives in 1999.
Biographical Note
Born in Milton, New Hampshire in 1887, Robert Edmond Jones graduated from Harvard University in 1910. Jones spent his career as a stage designer and rose to national prominence working with the Washington Square Players, Kenneth Macgowan and the Greenwich Village Theatre, Eugene O'Neill and the Provincetown Players, and the Theatre Guild, Inc. As a stage designer, Jones is best known for his simplified sets that complemented the action of a production and his dramatic use of color in costuming and lighting. In the 1930s, Jones was hired as a color consultant and designer by RKO studios, and worked on some of the first films to use the three-strip Technicolor process, Becky Sharp, La Cucaracha, and The Dancing Pirate. Jones published a number of articles on stagecraft, and authored Drawings for the Theatre (1925), The Dramatic Imagination (1941), and, with Kenneth Macgowan, Continental Stagecraft (1922).
Collection Overview
The Robert Edmond Jones Papers contains Jones's correspondence, both incoming and outgoing, his manuscript writings, drawings and design materials, photographs, and printed materials including clippings related to the many plays and films on which he worked during his long career as a stage designer and color consultant. The papers document Jones's work in theater as a set designer in the United States during the early twentieth century and his involvement in motion picture making during the 1930s.
Correspondence - Contains incoming and outgoing correspondence from 1934 to 1950.
Writings - Contains manuscript writings by Robert Edmond Jones on topics related to theater and stagecraft, acting and actors, and motion pictures. Included in the manuscript writings are four folders of Jones's recorded dreams from 1944 to 1945. Also contains writings of others about Robert Edmond Jones from 1916 to 1954.
Design - Contains materials used and created by Robert Edmond Jones in his stage design work. Includes sketches and drawings, printed material, and photographs.
Printed Materials - Contains clippings of reviews and articles relating to Jones's work in theater and film from 1916 to 1950, programs from 1919-1957. Within the Printed Materials series, a note from Jones to his mother, dated 1930 is included in the clippings for Symphony Hall. Also within Printed Materials is a note by Kenneth Macgowan, which is located in the folder of programs for Three Plays by Ridgley Torrence. Series also includes a scrapbook containing clippings related to Jones's work as a color consultant from 1933 to 1935.
Audio Recordings - Contains audio recordings of Robert Edmond Jones's lectures, dated 1955 and 1963.
Oversize Material - Contains photographs of set designs, materials related to costume design, and large drawings for set design.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is organized into six series: Correspondence, Writings, Design, Printed Materials, Audio Recordings, and Oversize Materials. Correspondence is further divided into two categories, incoming and outgoing, and is arranged alphabetically. Writings are arranged alphabetically by title or subject. Many of the writings remain unidentified, and have been kept with the materials with which they were originally filed. These unidentified manuscripts may be parts or fragments of other manuscript drafts or notes written by Jones. The Design series contains materials created or used by Jones in his design work. The materials are arranged by form. Additional drawings and design materials are located in the Oversize Materials series. Printed Materials consist of clippings, programs, and ephemera related to Jones's work in theater and film. Oversize materials consist mainly of large drawings and other design related materials and are arranged in alphabetical order by title of the play and drawing number.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Jones, Robert Edmond, 1887-1954.; Theater.; Theater --United States.; Theaters--Stage-setting and scenery--United States.; Motion pictures and theater.; Motion pictures--History.; Motion pictures--Setting and scenery.; Set designers--United States.; Set design--History--20th century.; Color cinematography--History.; Color motion pictures--History.; Scenography.; Design, stage.; Design, theater.; Design, set.; Architectural drawings (visual works)
Related Material
Jones, Robert Edmond, 1887-1954. Papers. Houghton Library, Harvard College Library. Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 02138.
Related Material
Jones, Robert Edmond, 1887-1954. Additional papers, 1911-1946. Houghton Library, Harvard College Library. Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 02138.
Related Material
Jones, Robert Edmond, 1887-1954. Additional papers, 1933-1952. Houghton Library, Harvard College Library. Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 02138.
Related Material
Jones, Robert Edmond, 1887-1954. Costume and set designs, 1932. Houghton Library, Harvard College Library. Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 02138.
Related Material
Robert Edmond Jones (1887-1954) Photographs. University of New Hampshire Library, 18 Library Way, Durham, NH 03824.
Related Material
Ralph Pendleton Papers, Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series 1: Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - Aherne, Brian, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1950 March (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Atkinson, Brooks, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Carey, Eleanor, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Cohen, Mark M., 1934 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes clippings about La Cucaracha.
    - Edwin Booth Dramatic Club, 1949 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Houghton, Norris, 1941 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Jeliffe, Belinda, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Jones, Fred P., Mrs., undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Lovejoy, A., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - The Players, Roy Day, 1941 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Reed, Joseph Verner, 1941 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Seldes, Gilbert, 1941 July 8 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Sisk, Robert, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Sloan, Samuel, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Vanity Fair, 1934-1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Wickes, Frances, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Wurzburg, Francis L., 1941 September (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Young, Stark, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Unidentified, 1935-1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Outgoing
    - Bing, Rudolf, 1950 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Jones, F. P. (Mrs.), 1936 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - New York Tribune, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Series II: Writings
  - "About Ignorant Criticism," holograph and typescript drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Around the Dawn," typescript fragment, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Color, holograph and typescript notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
  - "Curious and Profitable," pamphlet, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "The Drama of the Future," typescript draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Dreams, holograph and typescript drafts, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 31-34)
  - Epigrams, holograph and typescript drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Full-Color Motion Pictures to Revolutionize Industry," typescript draft, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "Illumination, Some Thoughts on Stage Lighting," holograph and typescript draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Lecture notes, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Lectures, holograph and typescript drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "Les Roses de la Vie," holograph and typescript drafts and notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Lines to a Critic," typescript draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Mid the Cool Olives of the Academe Fair Harvard," holograph draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Motion pictures, typescript notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Motion Pictures and the Theatre," typescript draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Movies and the Theatre," typescript draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "My Hollywood," typescript of published article from Vanity Fair, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Note on Isadora Duncan", undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Notes about Playwrights," holograph and typescript drafts and notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Notes and Lectures Regarding the Theatre," holograph and typescript notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Notes for a Talk about Stage Settings," typescript notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Notes for the New Ed." holograph and typescript notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Notes on John Barrymore," holograph and typescript notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Notes on Vaslav Nijinsky," holograph and typescript notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - On Reference Point, by Arthur Hopkins, typescript and holograph drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Reminiscences," holograph and typescript notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Review of Father Brown, by Chesterton, holograph draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Review of Scene, by Gordon Craig, holograph and typescript draft, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Review of Vogues of 1938, by Walter Wanger, holograph draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Sarah Bernhardt, holograph and typescript notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Setting, holograph and typescript notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - "Some Thoughts on Stage Design," typescript draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Stage Settings," typescript draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "The Question of Color," typescript drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Toward a New Theatre in America," typescript draft, 1950 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Working notes, holograph and typescript notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Unidentified manuscripts, notes, drafts and fragments, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-17)
  - Writings of Others
    - "Memorial Meeting for Robert Edmond Jones," transcript of event, 1954 December 12 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Moderwell, Hiram Kelly. "The Art of Robert Edmond Jones," transcribed from Theatre Arts Magazine, 1917 February (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Moderwell, Hiram Kelly. "Robert Edmond Jones: Young Leader of American Decorators for the Theatre," transcribed from Boston Evening Transcript, 1916 October 7 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Rodriquez, Jose. "Color at Last," typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Seldes, George. "Robert Edmond Jones Profile," transcribed from The New Yorker, 1931 May 9 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Young, Stark. "Note on Nijinsky and Robert Edmond Jones," typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Series III: Design
  - Drawings and Designs, Additional designs and drawings located in Oversize
    - [Medea?]. Small sketches, printed material, etc., undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Opera, sketches, notes, and printed material, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Original "Famous Artist Print" by Robert Edmond Jones. Fabric sample, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Drawings, Redemption, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Printed Material
    - Exhibition Catalogs, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Redemption, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Richard III, undated (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
  - Photographs
    - Jones, Robert Edmond. Inscribed to "Mother" and autographed, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Egyptian art and architecture, undated (Box 4, Folder 11-13)
- Series IV: Printed Materials
  - Clippings
    - Becky Sharp (film), 1935 (Box 4, Folder 14-16)
    - Becky Sharp (play), undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - The Birthday of the Infanta, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Biographical, 1916-1955 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Caliban, by the Yellow Sands, 1916 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Cherokee Night, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Color filmmaking, 1935-1936 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - La Cucaracha, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Daddy's Gone A-Hunting, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - The Dancing Pirate, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 6-8)
    - The Dramatic Imagination, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - The Enchanted, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Exhibitions, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Faust, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Garden of Paradise, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Die Glueckliche Hand, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Green Pastures, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - The Hairy Ape, 1922 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Hamlet, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Helen Goes to Troy, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Holiday, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Hopkins, Arthur, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - The Jest, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Ladies Leave, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - The Living Mask, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Lucrece, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Lute Songs, 1946-1947 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Macbeth, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Machinal, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Martine, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Mary of Scotland, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - A Moon for the Misbegotten, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Mr. Moneypenny, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - The Mountain Man, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Obituaries, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - O'Neill, Eugene, 1953, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Othello, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - The Philadelphia Story, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Pierrot Lunaire, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Radio City Music Hall, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Redemption, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - The Rescuing Angel, 1917 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Richard III, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - The Saint, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Serena Blandish, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Skyscrapers, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Symphony Hall. Includes note from REJ to Mother., 1930 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - These Days, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Tyl Eulenspiegel, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Wozzeck, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Yolanda of Cyprus, 1929-1930 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Programs
    - Central City, 1932-1941 (Box 6, Folder 15-16)
    - Die Glueckliche Hand, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Hamlet, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Helen Goes to Troy, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Out of Dust, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Three Plays by Ridgley Torrence. Includes note by Kenneth Macgowan., circa 1919, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Other Printed Material
    - Chrysalis: Robert Edmond Jones, pamphlet, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous material, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Scrapbook, 1933-1935 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      Contains clippings related to Jones's work as a color consultant in early Technicolor filmmaking.
- Series V: Audio Recordings
  - Jones, Robert Edmond, and Frederick C. Packard. Towards a New Theatre [Sound Recording] / Robert Edmond Jones. (2 LP disks), 1955 (Box 7)
  - Jones, Robert Edmond. Towards a New Theatre, Also Curious and Profitable Lectures to Drama Students. Brunswick, Me: Vocarium Records, Inc. Reel-to-reel, 1963 (Box 7)
- Series VI: Oversize Material
  - Various large photographs of scene designs, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Green Pastures. Costume design boards, photographs, and printed material (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - The Jew of Malta, costume design. Paintings and printed material, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook containing photographs of Jones's stage designs, undated (Box 8)
  - Oversize Drawings and Designs
    - A Touch of the Poet, 1946 (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [69-C11] Side Elevation of Beams (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [69-C13] Corner Cabinet (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [69-C17] Plan (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [69-C20] 4 Sliding Shutters (Box Oversize Drawer)
    - Enchanted, 1949 (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Act I, Act II: Detail of Trees (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Act I, Act II: Revised Plan (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Act III Ground Plan (Box Oversize Drawer)
    - Green Pastures, 1949 (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Act II, Scene VII: Outside a Temple (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Ark (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Throne Room (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Woodwings and Foliage Borders (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Fish-fry Tree Trunk (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Office (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Sunday School (Box Oversize Drawer)
    - The Joyous Season, Curtains for Bay Window, undated (Box Oversize Drawer)
    - Lute Song, 1945 (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Rock in Pavillion (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Scene I (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Sliding Screens (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - A Place of Light and Flowers (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Front Curtain 1 (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Front Curtain 2 (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Shrine (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Temple: Buddha and Pedestal (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Untitled (4 designs) (Box Oversize Drawer)
    - Othello, 1943 (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C2] First Inner Proscenium - Ground Plan (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C2] Second Inner Proscenium - Ground Plan (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C3] Set #1 Ground Plan (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C4] Set #1 Elevation (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C5] Act I, Scene I: A Street - Ground Plan (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C6] Act I, Scene II: Senate Chamber - Ground Plan (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C8] Act I, Sc. II: Plaque to cover window opening (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C9] Act ---, Scene ---: Arrival in Cyprus - Ground Plan (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C10] Act II, Scene ---: A Wharf - Ground Plan (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C11] Act ---, Scene ---: Courtyard - Ground Plan (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C13] Set # 2 Ground Plan (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C14] Set #2 Elevation (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C16] Set #3 Backings (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C17] Final Scene - Bed, Headboard, Backing (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C18] Final Scene - Detail of Headboard of Bed (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C19] 2 Transparent Muslin Drops (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - [64-C21] Permanent Ground Row (Box Oversize Drawer)
    - Out of Dust, 1949 (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Act I, Scene I (2 sheets) (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Act I, Scene II (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Act I, Scene III (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Act II, Scene I (2 sheets) (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Act II, Scene II (2 sheets) (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Covered Wagon (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Frame for Drops (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Method of Hanging Drops for "Out of Dust" (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Portal (1 drawing, 3 blueprint copies) (Box Oversize Drawer)
      - Working Drawings for Deserted Shack for "Out of Dust" (Box Oversize Drawer)
    - Unidentified drawings, undated (Box Oversize Drawer)